<div><p ><div>But He also further benefits them by immediately adding; <b>"But in this rejoice not, that the spirits are subject unto you; but rather rejoice that your names are written in heaven."</b>: 'Dost Thou not, O Lord, permit those who have been honoured by Thee to rejoice in their honours? And yet it is written of those who were appointed to the apostleship: "They shall walk, O Lord, in the light of Thy countenance, and in Thy name shall they exult all the day, and in Thy righteousness shall they be exalted. For Thou art the glory of their strength, and in Thy good pleasure shall our horn be exalted." How then didst Thou command them not to rejoice in the honour and glory which Thou didst Thyself bestow?' What can we say to this? I answer, that Christ raises them to something greater, and commands them to account it their glory that their names were written in heaven. For it is of the saints that God is thus addressed, "And in Thy book they are all written."<br />But besides, to rejoice solely in the fact that they were able to work miracles, and crush the herds of demons, was likely to produce in them possibly the desire also of vainglory:----and the neighbour, so to speak, and kinsfellow of this passion constantly is pride. Most usefully, therefore, does the Saviour of all rebuke the first boasting, and quickly cuts away the root, so to speak, that had sprung up in them of the base love of glory, imitating good husbandmen, who, immediately that they see a thorn springing up in their pleasure grounds or gardens, tear it up with the teeth of the mattock, before it strike its root deep.<br />Even though, therefore, we receive some gift from Christ not unworthy of admiration, we must not think too highly of it, but rather make the hope prepared for us our cause of rejoicing, and that our names are written in the companies of the saints, by Christ's gift, the Saviour of us all, Who, from His love to man bestows, with all besides that we have, this also upon us: by Whom, and with Whom, to God the Father be praise and dominion with the Holy Ghost, for ever and ever, Amen.</div></p>
<div class="text-center">
<a id="left_arrow" href="/commentaries/?b=490&c=10&v=19">&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;</a>
<a id="bottom_home" href="/commentaries/footnotes/?f=1044">&emsp;&emsp;</a>
<a id="right_arrow" href="/commentaries/?b=490&c=10&v=21">&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;</a>
</div>
</div>