<div><p ><div>Why, Lord, do you tell me to make such a purchase, when you have forbidden me to strike back (ср. <a href="/bible-index/bible/?b=470&c=26&s=52"><span><span class="verse-text"><span class="align-super">52</span> Тогда говорит ему Иисус: возврати меч твой в его место, ибо все, взявшие меч, мечом погибнут;</span></span>Мф. 26:52</a>): Why do you tell me to have a sword that I am not allowed to draw from its scabbard? Maybe it is for purposes of defence, but not of vengeance - to show that you could avenge yourself, but did not choose to do so. The Law, however, does not forbid me to strike back. So perhaps that is why you say to Peter, when He offers you two swords, <b>“That is enough"</b> (<a href="/bible-index/bible/?b=490&c=22&s=38"><span><span class="verse-text"><span class="align-super">38</span> Они сказали: Господи! вот, здесь два меча. Он сказал им: довольно.</span></span>Лк. 22:38</a>). It is as if you are saying that to strike back was allowable up to the time of the Gospel; and that the Law gave us the rudiments of justice, but the Gospel gives the finishing touch of kindness and mercy.<br /><br />Many people are shocked by these words, but the Lord is not doing anything wrong. He could have taken revenge; instead, He sacrificed Himself. Remember, too, that there is a spiritual sword, and that spiritual sword obliges you to sell your inheritance to buy the word that will clothe the inmost recesses of your soul.<br /><br />There is, too, the sword of the Passion which makes us strip off the body and to purchase, with the spoils of the body, the holy crown of martyrdom. But this we could have concluded for ourselves from the Lord's own words in the Beatitudes. For there He tells us that the crown of all crowns goes to those who suffer persecution for the sake of justice (cf. <a href="/bible-index/bible/?b=470&c=5&s=10"><span><span class="verse-text"><span class="align-super">10</span> Блаженны изгнанные за правду, ибо их есть Царство Небесное.</span></span>Мф. 5:10</a>). To prove to you that He is speaking of the Passion, and without wanting to dishearten His disciples, He gives Himself as an example. He says: <b>“What has been written must be accomplished in Me: He has been numbered among the unjust”</b> (<a href="/bible-index/bible/?b=490&c=22&s=37"><span><span class="verse-text"><span class="align-super">37</span> ибо сказываю вам, что должно исполниться на Мне и сему написанному: и к злодеям причтен. Ибо то, что о Мне, приходит к концу.</span></span>Лк. 22:37</a>).<br /><br />There are however, various interpretations of the two swords that the disciples offer to the Lord. One sword might possibly stand for the New Testament, and the other for the Old. With these weapons we are armed "<i>against the deceits of the devil"</i> (<a href="/bible-index/bible/?b=560&c=6&s=11"><span><span class="verse-text"><span class="align-super">11</span> Облекитесь во всеоружие Божие, чтобы вам можно было стать против козней диавольских,</span></span>Еф. 6:11</a>). Also, when our Lord says: “That is enough", He could be indicating that there is nothing lacking to one who is fortified by the teaching of the two Testaments.</div></p>
<div class="text-center">
<a id="left_arrow" href="/commentaries/?b=490&c=12&v=10">&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;</a>
<a id="bottom_home" href="/commentaries/footnotes/?f=1029">&emsp;&emsp;</a>
<a id="right_arrow" href="/commentaries/?b=490&c=23&v=9">&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;</a>
</div>
</div>